watch your B
just one object in the world with
breath tie the mind with breath try to
feel a sensation of the Mind tied to the
breath e
come to the golden
Golden Light late afternoon sun point
very beautiful
sky e
beauti
B covered with the L light and mountains
in the
distance e
inside ask you teacher to come face
okay you up into their face which is
also covered with the golden light
look into their their eyes to so much
love
just stay there with a feeling of
contentment that I don't have to go
anywhere else I don't have anything else
to
do what I need is
here e
if you lose your teacher's eyes use
your session to detect it
you turn about to bring it back
try to feel
my
e
e e
back to your teaches
a sense of
contentment
e
e e
slowly come back to this room
uh that was much longer and it felt good
I think
uh you're ready for that it felt
good I think now we can
start increasing the time little yeah so
it felt I it felt really really good in
the room and it felt very very
concentrated you know if you move or if
you sniffle you you disturb the what do
you call you dve the the thw of the room
right but
uh but also if you think of something
else you disturb the the
room and uh I like it because everyone's
thinking of the golden room at the same
time and and to me the golden room for
me is much brighter than it's ever been
and I feel like if we're supporting each
other me mentally right inside the mind
so
so in the same way that you wouldn't
want to crinkle some potato chip bag
during our
meditation
uh feel feel a feel a desire not to want
to disturb the other Mind by not being
there in your own mind you see because
we feel everyone feels it right uh and
right now it's it's fantastic right now
though
the meditation strength is really
beautiful all
right so we'll do a little more uh let
me think about it let's uh let's do one
or two questions those are entertaining
right
okay uh I am in a meeting with a certain
person and my holy llama comes into the
room and says you stole a book my
immediate reaction is I did not but
because I just came from these teachings
I realized the emptiness of all concern
and the kic
relationships however my llama whom I
project as God and I can because that
llama is empty says I must leave the
most important thing in my life these
teachings of course I know this came
from something like my stealing candy
when I was 10 from the
7-Eleven I regret that past Karma and
have tried to do the for Powers all fine
and dandy
intellectually but what must be dealt
with on a deceptive level to be able to
get the teachings now to stop this and
then there's a word for
poooo uh but not the one you're
thinking
uh that's easy I mean
uh to have teachings on emptiness
especially uh is one of the most
expensive credit hardly expensive events
in in a human existence okay so you born
with a certain credit
card uh it's a debit card
actually uh it was loaded in your last
life or in the that and the previous
life so the card was loaded and then you
come into this life and then you
start experiencing things and every time
you experience anything you're using up
your credit card your debit card and
it's approaching zero when it approaches
zero you
die I don't know if you've ever noticed
how a person's life wraps up in many
different ways as as in the final weeks
of their life you know just everything
starts messing up you know not just your
health but you know there's family
problems you lose your house you lose
your car you lose your spouse
everything when Karma winds down
it winds down in a comprehensive way you
know and then everything starts to go at
the same
time and then your and then your debit
card is cashed in and then you're that's
it it's at zero and you die but it it
everything lies down at the same time
like we feel
upset if someone takes something from us
or breaks something of ours or
or you know scratches my
body or calls me names but on the day
that you die all the insults of of an
entire life are rendered on in a single
hour you know like not only do they
scratch your body they take the whole
thing and not only do they you know yell
at you it's you can't hear anymore and
you know all of those little uh injuries
are all rought on you in in an hour a
whole life's injuries are are are piled
on you in the final hour and then uh and
then the card runs out
okay and to have
teachings is is one of the most
expensive uses of the card okay so uh
they like having a teacher a living
teacher uh who's who can be who you can
be
around and having teachings on on
something
extraordinary uh these are like I don't
know walking into what's that place on
the park and
f b do Goodman you know like you can't
even walk in there for less than $500
uh like you say I'm going to buy my
friend a gift from burog Gman and you
walk in there and the only thing you can
afford is some gloves or a scarf or
something it's already
$400 uh so being around a living teacher
especially your heart teacher and also
receiving teachings especially on
meditational emptiness these are
extremely
expensive and and whenever you whatever
I love that song from s mus do you know
which one I'm talking
about something somewhere in
my
child I
must you're like uh what did I do to get
a teacher in my life you know what did I
do to get these teachings and then uh
because just by sitting here you are
running up huge bill
you know the I mean the karma to be in
this room is is is the most expensive
karma in the
earth and it uses up the most Good Deeds
of any Karma to be in the presence of a
living teacher and and to study
emptiness or or meditation is is uh the
most expensive it's the fastest way to
draw down your debit cards uh
so then you have to do something to keep
it charged up right you have to fight
that tendency you have to have a you
know a wealthy friend who who does
direct deposits you
know and
uh and that's
teaching okay that's teaching teaching
other people what you've heard is a
wealthy friend who does direct
deposits okay and that's all so whoever
wrote that paper actually I know who
wrote that paper uh all all all what do
you call it all
problems with uh karmic call karmic seed
deficits or kic seed down what do you
call it draw Downs uh they can be fixed
universally by teaching okay so uh and
also teaching is a lot of fun I mean to
sit there and try to concentrate for two
hours is ex
cruciating uh but to stand up sit up
here and to blab for two hours is easy
you know because you get to be it's so
egotistical so
uh so it's not only karmically powerful
it's also the I mean it's the best thing
for your ego and and it's the best thing
for your debit card your caric debit
card so it's kind of a happy coincidence
that the best thing for your credit
debit card is what's most fun and does
the most for your ego okay uh in a good
way and a bad way uh so teach you know
and then you will have teachings you see
like I I teach constantly and I don't
always teach with a very you know with a
perfect motivation but
um but because I teach constantly I
always have people teaching me all the
time and it's wonderful you know like I
go to I go to yoga classes or uh I try
to learn languages or or just I try to
learn how to grow roses and always a
teacher shows up and somebody beautiful
somebody
wonderful and
uh you know people come to my garage and
teach me yoga you know and
uh so if
you if you have a problem with some
obstacles to going to teachings or
taking teachings then the best thing and
the funnest thing and the most effective
thing is just to teach and teaching
doesn't have to
be
uh teaching doesn't have to be 200
people you know teaching can be a lot of
I think a lot of the best teachings go
down between friends over
coffee I think some of the most
significant teachings happen between
friends uh over over tea or coffee and
uh and and maybe they are more they are
more powerful than group teachings uh or
formal teachings I think uh you're more
likely to
accept something from a person who is
speaking to you one oneon-one
sincerely then it changes your heart
more than going to a big you know
Retreat and like that
so so teach just teach okay and then you
will have all the teachings you
want and it's
fun and it's fun to be taught I I crave
being taught I love being taught and I
just really enjoy
it so
I went to Allison's class in New York we
know each other for I don't know longer
than we want to
say uh but I never been to her class and
then uh Alan took me one day and
uh it was it was really I don't know I
just feel like I'm in somebody's arms
when I go to a class and I
love the the feeling of being taught by
somebody and
uh so so you to the only way you can get
that is to teach you have to
teach and if you not don't have enough
teachings you have to teach more that's
the good thing about Karma R Used To
Tell me uh I remember one day I walked
into his room and he and he and he
looked at me and he said some SAR is so
great you know and I'm like you know and
I he was he was ulent you know he was
like bubbling over he's like SAR is so
great you know and I'm
like what you know like I just got back
from New York I was all tired you know I
was like what I said Samar is the design
of Samar is so perfect you know and I'm
like what do you mean r Chene says
uh well whatever
you whatever you need some Sor tells
you you know
so I said what do you mean he says like
if you needed teachings and you weren't
getting enough
teachings
uh Samar would would tell you that you
you needed to to teach more you see what
I mean uh what you're not doing samsar
will tell you to
do that's what I mean if you're not
getting enough teaching some Sor will
inform
you uh of what you need to do that you
need to do something more okay so if
it's if if something happening to you is
not
enough uh sasara will inform you that
you have to do more of the opposite for
somebody else right you have to do more
of that for somebody
else and RI was so happy you know it's
like you don't have to figure out what
to do so s will tell you that you're not
teaching enough because you won't get
enough
teachings okay m let's go back to
the and we're up to
24 oh sorry we finished 24 right and now
we're we're moving on to 25 what has
happened to the
elephant uh for the first time he's all
white like I don't know if you notice
here but between 24 and
25 the back of his leg is a little black
okay all right and then uh
it goes away and in 25 the elephant is
all white
again so I'll read you the translation
of the Tibetan here hear the fact that
the elephant has lost all the black and
Left Behind the monkey as
well a the monkey
got he looks like he's paying to
go he got left behind here
and Left Behind the monkey as well
represents your ability to engage in
one-pointed
concentration in an uninterrupted
stream and we talked about what one
pointed means right what's one pointed
mean one object okay just it's so easy
it's so
uncomplicated meditation is just putting
your mind on one thing and that's it
that's all and and I I go to shivana
Center teach sometimes there's a nice
Swami there
called RAR Rupa Nanda or
something uh their names get longer the
longer the lineage goes on
uh
noar who SW student the tall guy is
really
br br manand okay anyway
uh he's they're kind of simple there
they don't have like very you
know they don't have teachings like we
have which is too bad but they but but I
I they have really really good uh some
beautiful things are happening there so
he will get sit down and he'll lead a
meditation and he's just saying you know
forget about where you have to go forget
about what's for lunch forget about the
temple forget about everybody around you
just think about this one thing and
that's that's a good instruction that's
uh that's meditation just put your mind
on a single thing you know if if you
can't do anything when you go
home you know on Sunday or Monday just
try to remember that meditation means
the ability to put your mind on one
thing and one thing only and that's all
then whatever you're doing is
meditation just one
thing in your mind
so anyway he reached uh say chi one
pointed concentration if you apply just
a little effort to bring your mind to
the object and to maintain watchfulness
then dullness agitation and distraction
can no longer interrupt your meditation
okay so with minimal
effort at number
25 nothing can interrupt your meditation
you are one pointed and then at
26 he's called uh s
cha say CH TOA which
is level eight okay single pointed this
eag eag is e plus Agra
Agra okay Agra means a a
point okay uh so here's how it's
described in the text this level eight
we're at level eight now
okay it's getting increasingly
theoretical for most of
us all right anyway uh a minimal effort
at the start allows the entire session
to continue without even the subtle
forms of agitation and
dullness no
expend no expenditure of effort is
required by sh at all there's no there's
no not the slightest expenditure of
effort by by the state of mind which
which the alarm State of Mind okay
there's no it
doesn't it's effortless
now and so this level is is
differentiated or distinguished from the
previous level in that you have no forms
of d s agitation anymore there's no not
even subtle form nothing no dullness and
no agitation at
level8 level eight and level seven are
complished to the power of making effort
subtle effort
okay and there's a new State of Mind
here there's a new feeling of of the
meditation we've what have we had as far
as feeling of the
med uh you have to sort of call it set
your mind to it okay and then and then
you meditate so some conscious effort to
meditate and then in the
second uh level it was
what
oh well that was the first two levels
I'm sorry first two levels uh you have
to you have to screw up your
concentration screw down I don't
know uh you have to gather your
concentration and then from levels three
to level
seven uh you have this sensation of uh
meditating but being tapped on the
shoulder more or less
frequently okay more or less frequently
and now we're on level eight it's
called means there's no more what do you
call it tap on the shoulder there's
simply no your the mind is Flowing the
meditation is flowing and there's no
longer any uh Gap There's No
Interruption at all nobody's dullness
and agitation are not there and there's
no interruption in the flow of the
meditation how could it get better than
that okay remember we our goal is to get
to 9 plus we're supposed to get to 9 and
then we're supposed to go a little
farther somehow which we have to talk
about okay we have to talk about that
this is in this is Sam this is single
point in mind level eight is already
some money okay so so where are we going
after that what what do we have to do
now how come that's not enough all right
what could be
better uh we'll go what's next
uh yeah oh sorry what does 27 say let me
see the power of complete habituation
which allows you to reach the ninth
metal
state so 27 over here above the
fruits uh that's called
y
okay it's the last impetus that's
required to get you to Stage Nine to
level N9 okay and that's yoga means uh
you are completely familiar with the
thing you just what do you call it total
habituation fluid you are
fluid you you've been through the
process of the first eight levels so
many times that that is just you're un
automatic okay so yunga means constant
practice and habituation okay you're so
you're so used to being in a Groove that
you get there automatically with no Cons
with no conscious effort okay that'sa
and then that that's the only thing
that's required to throw you into level
n okay to get you to level n what is
love online uh the name
isaa Isa means
Sumer uh
and J
means so
is
Sam Samar has a lot of different
meanings and different Traditions okay
in the yoga
Sutra uh Samari has a unique meaning and
even in different chapters it has a
different meaning uh so what it Samar
means here
is this is how the text described
it okay now we get into a new subject
should we meditate
first
yeah we'll do it tomorrow okay we'll do
it
tomorrow
uh a state of mind which is still in the
desire room and then we have to that's
going to open a can of worms tomorrow
okay this is the highest state of
concentration which you can have and
still be in the
desire what's a desire realm it's a it's
a world where people's interests are
driven by food and
sex
basically a whole realm of people who
are here and whose whose most
Primal uh desires are fuit and and then
why why not level 9 is called a desire
realm state of mind or the highest
desire realm state of
mind uh will give us a clue of how we
get past Lev of life and go to where we
got to go to reach the meditative
platform that is necessary to see
emptiness so just those words na n is
the highest state of meditation in the
desire R and then tomorrow we'll go
I think what's really interesting to me
is why do you have to go past the L of
mind what is
it what is left and what do you have to
do what extra thing do you have to do to
just to get to
the to the degree of meditation that you
require to see emperically okay because
that's why we're
meditating okay all right let's meditate
some
more some people told me they're having
trouble sitting so
long then sit on a chair okay if
there're not enough chairs talk
to
Jared okay but don't don't suffer don't
there's you don't get any points for how
you look because you're not looking you
got your eyes
closed and while you're meditating the
rest of us are eating these
cookies so we don't care what you look
like it just doesn't matter at all
doesn't matter if you're sitting on the
ground it just doesn't matter at all
what matters is if you sit in a place
which is uncomfortable for you and then
your body is screaming you won't be able
to concentrate so that's
counterproductive right that's the
opposite of what you want to do you want
to find a position which is completely
comfortable without lying down
okay watch your
B
e e
come to the golden
room e
look out the window this guy
and this pleas cut
cut the B um it's you for
me e
then come back to the golden room
it's warm it's
bright soft golden
color all the objects in the room are
covered with a soft golden
light and
you request your teacher to come
they sit in front of you me to meet
now once again just focus on their
presence just feel a single object of
your meditation is their
present the feeling of their
presence e
well on bring on a sense of contentment
to be in this room with your
teacher I don't need to go anywhere else
I don't need to be with anyone else I
don't need to think about anything else
I don't need to look at anything
else just
be the presence of my
teacher that in now
inde
e
e e
and slowly come back to the
sweep then come
H that was awesome that was really
awesome really awesome really good
amazing yeah
good uh
if if we were really engrossed in the
I'm re re rephrasing it okay if we were
really engrossed in the
object
uh why would we need the Watcher or the
other guy okay the polar backer
guy okay why would we need the Watcher
guy and the polar backer
guy if uh if we were totally engrossed
in a virtual subject
you know frankly I never noticed it
before but
uh do you notice anything different
about the
monk between 22 24 and
26 you can't answer it what yeah he's
not holding anything
anymore okay he's not holding anything
anymore all right
I think at 22 when your watch your mind
becomes most fully developed
right which brings you into level
seven I've never really noticed it
before but he doesn't have anything in
his hands
anymore uh and they
say let's go back to the five problems
and the eight antidotes and our answer
will be there okay so we haven't talked
much about them
recently okay what that's not on the
chart necessarily
okay what was the first problem of
meditation yeah yeah Brandy went like
this uh you don't feel maybe you should
go like this you
know maybe
tomorrow you know so number one
meditation problem is uh I just don't
feel like
it it's not evil but it is
evil yeah it's an innocent state of mind
right I just don't feel like it today
I'll start
tomorrow you know I'll start my Spanish
studies my Chinese studies and my uh
meditation tomorrow because today I'm
tired I I just got off the plane and uh
you know I don't feel so good and uh
let's just do it tomorrow okay so that's
the first meditation problem I don't
feel like it it's such an innocent thing
to say and it's such an innocent State
of Mind
and it ruins you it ruins everybody it
it keeps you from you know why why can I
teach
this uh just my teacher pushed me you
know he didn't give me a break I didn't
have a break for 20 years 25 years he he
pushed me you know and uh really hard
and never satisfied and never never
praising me ever he just push push push
it wouldn't give me like I didn't have 3
minutes break you know they I went to
work for the Israeli the crazy Israeli
in New York who worked us 18 hours a day
I felt
glad you know I was like ah you know
people thought it's crazy you know like
this is heaven you know
so uh Leo is like I I just don't feel
like it okay then and then we said the
antidotes
what it Shin which means uh think about
how cool it is if you learn to
meditate I don't know if you if you ever
have any special experience in
meditation then you've got that
cover if you ever like see the future
or you know something extraordinary
happens to you you got that cover Dumba
means I want it so means I'm wear
willing to work for it Shin Jang means
once I get good at it it's going to be
cool
we uh before we went into threee Retreat
Lama Christie and I uh went to see Lady
Ruth laow at J mukti cuz she was one of
our teachers yoga teachers and uh we
said uh she gave us a class in that
little side room which is kind of a
difficult place over
class uh it's a little corner tiny
little room it's not even a room really
it's like a closet and so we had you
can't have two people do do a in the
there kind of anyway so we we went to
the Osos and then we we we were saying
goodbye for three years and then we said
by the way can you show us how to do
some assists because maybe we'll have to
assist each other in the in the yoga in
our year maybe it'd be helpful to know
how not to hurt somebody in the assist
so then she uh she said okay I'll be the
student you be the teacher and I'll show
you what to do and then she started to
she said okay I'm going to take this
pose and then you're going to you're
going to assist me like this and then we
would she would take the pose and we
would do the assist and she'd go
ah you know every every time we touched
her every time we just pushed her a
little bit like just twist her a little
bit further she'd go this involuntary ah
would come out you
know that's Shin Jang for yoga you know
she's she's at such a high state of yoga
that every pose is pleasurable to her uh
you know so that's sh that's number four
once every pose is pleasurable or once
every meditation experience is highly
pleasurable you will want to not do your
meditation okay all right so that's the
four antidotes to the first problem what
was the second problem you can't was the
second
problem
uh for yeah for it's called forgetting
the instructions but what it means is
losing the object okay
and what's the fix for
that Tamba is bringing your mind back to
the object okay it's just the left hand
thing it's just the chain okay
uh then the third meditation problem is
is ch ch it means uh dullness and
agitation either and or either or either
or
and I know we had this big debate allas
yogis about the inner
body uh about whether you could have a
and udav operating at the same
moment because udav is what raises
things through the body like
speech and then aavo is what eliminates
things from the body and every V is the
momentary Gathering of all the other
Prana of the body to to accomplish a
purpose so we had this very serious
debate going about whether you could
have a danav and a panav working at the
same time and then we went to this te-
shop in
barasi and we ate the
the we ate the deep fried things there
and we got out the
door uh I got to the other side of the
road I don't know if La chrisy got the
other side of the road but but we got
out the door and then I ran to a ditch
on the other side and I had a udana and
a at the same
moment but maybe it was toggling I don't
[Applause]
know why did I talk about
that third meditation
oh yeah could you have dullness and
agitation at the same
time that's interesting question
probably we could
manage uh you know could you think about
lunch and fall asleep at the same time
uh let's
try
okay then traditionally they say that
traditionally they say the traditional
antidote for number three is not the
real antidote okay by Trad tradtion
we're supposed to tell you that the
traditional antidote for number three is
not the real antidote because if the
antidote for number three is the thing
in his right hand which is Shan or the
alarm okay just being aware you have a
problem doesn't fix the problem so
technically
speaking uh the awareness that you're
having a problem doesn't fix dullness
and
agitation and and in all the great
llamas of History starting with Arya I
think they said okay look I know I know
I know that uh this is not really the
antidote but you have to have it to get
to the antidote okay then the real
antidote is is the antidote to number
four okay so number four the problem
number four is number
D which means
uh failing to take action when you
detect dness or agitation failing to
take action not not taking the required
action when you detect that you're dull
or agitated okay what would the actions
be for
dullness you can think how lucky you are
uh you can think of your boyfriend you
can think of something bright you can
even think of a of a gold the the point
of the Gold Room is even something
physically colored
bright imagine in the mind can raise the
mind out of dullness okay you can't get
enough sleep you cannot eat meals before
you meditate there are there are lots of
fixes for dullness you can s uplift the
Mind what's the fixes for
agitation uh bring the Mind down a
little bit okay I find that a list of
five people I know who died and I'm not
a gross person you know I don't spend my
time thinking I've had lots of people
die in my life and I got over it I'm I
know I'm doing my life you know and I
wish them well but I can't do anything
about it and I don't worry about it uh
but but just thinking of five people who
died is enough to bring my mind out of
lunch you can't think about lunch and
about three people who died in your life
at the same time I don't think it's
possible okay so it'll bring your mind
down something like that
uh those are the antidotes okay so
numbera not applying the antidote is
problem number four and it's fixed by H
applying the antidote okay so fix number
four is applying the antidote why am I
talking about this because in my usual
long-winded Gushi microw I'm and
sometimes I forget where I was going and
I just go somewhere else but now I do
remember where I was
going uh problem number five
is
number which means taking action when
it's no longer necessary that's a cool
that's cool that they recognize that as
a problem right it's cool that that
should be the final problem of your
meditation like we had a we had a huge
Factory we did 30,000 Rings a day that's
300,000 Stones a day if you if you have
300,000 stones that that means you have
to sort million Stones a day and uh and
we did it you know and we had a huge
Factory and we were pumping big bags of
diamonds down to the factory you know
and
uh we'd have these really huge meetings
about you know how do you make 30,000
pieces of Jewelry in a day and and not
have any defects you know and then uh we
would look into each department and try
to we'd have a big meeting the Rings are
we get a package of ring back from JC
Penny they say they're scratched we'
have a big meeting we would uh decide
to you know investigate all the
Departments of the Factory and then uh
we'd go down and tell the factory
manager you know we're going to
investigate all the departments in
Factory find out where the cracks are
coming you know scratches are coming
from and he'd say he'd look at us he's
this big F lazy guy and he'd say if it
ain't broke don't fix
it okay if it ain't broke don't fix it
you know like okay you're get a few with
scratches but if you mess around with
every Department you're G to get more
okay so there's a point in your life at
which you should learn to not mess
around with something if it ain't so bad
just leave it alone because sometimes
trying to fix it will make it worse
right if it ain't broke don't fix it
okay uh
so problem number five
is is is overdoing the corrections or
and and that's the answer eventually to
the person's question uh would you still
need the sh in DEA would you still need
watchfulness and the ability to pull the
Mind back if you had a very sexy object
that you were in love with and you were
Eng grossed with and you didn't have you
were on a rooll with that object yeah
the answer to your question is uh
meditation problem number five if it
ain't broke don't fix it if if you
medal into the flow which is going nice
if if you if your mind is Flowing easy
on this highly attractive object to you
like your teacher and then suddenly
you're like hey are we having any
agitation hey are we having any
agitation you're like sh I'm
meditating is the mine off the arm in
shut up
okay so yeah you do get to a point
where where checking becomes an obstacle
and that's that's number five that's
classical problem number five actually I
think you just got your whole
thing well not quite we don't have nine
plus yet so you got the nine levels you
got the six Powers you got the four
states of
mine I got one more St in mind and you
got but you did get the five problems
and the eight antidotes you should be
able them off by the end of the week
okay all right one more
question
no yeah let's do one
more I like the yellow one I don't know
why okay this is a tough
question this person basically the
question boils down to uh it's a great
honor and a great goodness and a great
pleasure to serve your teacher you know
even if it's not your heart teacher like
it's just a med meditation teacher is
doing the week okay and then
uh and then you want to you want to get
an opportunity to to do anything for
them you know but there's this crowd of
this of you
know what do you call there's The In
Crowd and they're
like you know we don't need any help
thanks you know so uh
what should I do about
that
uh I well my own experience you know I
was R's
attendant uh for I don't know well we
had other attendants later that helped
but uh you know I don't know 20 years 25
years and and I would say a couple of
things uh one is that if you are an
attendant or if you're close to the
llama and you want to stay close to the
Llama what do you have to do I mean you
have to allow access you know your your
main uh goal as an attendant your only
goal really is to allow responsible
access to the teacher so the actually
the teacher shouldn't get burned out or
you know have thousands of people like
crowding into their room or something uh
but but but I always felt that my job
with
rache was to that anyone who wanted to
see him should see him you know even if
there were like really irritating
people uh and if they were super unless
they were going to hurt him or something
but I I always felt like my job for 25
years was uh make sure everyone can get
to serve him or gets a chance to help
him or gets a chance to see him or
anybody can get in to be with him and
and I really did do that and it was fun
and I didn't feel
like I was being short changed or
something cuz by doing that karmically
you get to be closer than anybody else
and that's what happened you know so he
was I was the only person that could go
up and like what do you call it talk
baseball with him or gossip with him you
know that he felt comfortable enough to
sit there and gossip with me you know
and it was fun uh so I think uh from the
attendant point of view or the helper
point of view if you make it your
goal that people should have access and
you find ways to create that access
without burning out the teacher you know
so that's a balance right then
uh from the point of view of a person
who would like to serve or who would
like to get into the service area you
know uh I would say in my own opinion is
the uh willingness to take on really
dirty jobs really thankless dirty jobs
for example
accounting okay so I was rased pendant
but I was also his accountant for 25
years and I took care of all his
finances he didn't know anything he
never saw a bill and he didn't know
where the money came from or he didn't
know anything and it was hard and I kept
very careful books I had a computer
program and we kept books and he never
saw them and he got Social Security
you know we did you have to have 40
quarters to to get it for the rest of
your life we squished him in we got him
in the last week 40 quarters we got him
in he got social security for the rest
of his life he didn't know anything he
just said this is so nice the government
has sent me a check every we you know
and it took like months of work uh to
make it happen it was really hard to
make it happen
so uh I I remember complaining to my
other teacher gessi T mention you know I
said he said how's it going you know I
said I don't know you know this
accounting everything's okay except I
hate accounting I really hate accounting
and I have to do the accounting and he
looks at me and he says oh my God don't
you know who was the accountant for
Mander
Monastery and I said no I don't know he
said
Nar you know and I said I didn't know
that he said yeah yeah the G was the
accountant you know and I said well why
you and
he said uh Mis misuse of Dharma funds is
one of the most serious bad karmas a
person can do you know the misuse of
funds collected for for the purpose of
propagating the Dharma is one of the
most serious bad karmas a person can do
so they assigned Aran nag to take care
of the books because everybody else was
afraid to touch that Karma they didn't
want to make a mistake with the with the
S money and and then uh to tell you the
truth what happened after that was uh AA
they had a financial pinch which is
typical in religious organizations and
um so he thought well I'll just make
some
gold and uh he was an
alchemist and uh so he made some gold
and he paid off the you know the bills
and then he and then the monastery found
out and they dug out some ancient rule
that said monks aren't allowed to do
alchemy you know and they fired him
and they asked him to leave the
monastery he had to leave the monastery
so you know but anyway
uh
uhin was like guy you your account
that's that's an honor it means that
they really trust you and they believe
you're like the person who can handle
that hot Karma you know so he was like
you should be happy so I would say to
get into the close to get
close uh it would be in my mind the
willingness to take on like the really
lousy jobs you know to sit there and
make the llamas tea and then you get to
sit there with them and and chat with
them is is
uh you know that's one Karma but the but
you know doing the accounts for this
Retreat uh now that's a no that's a big
Karma and then that would Propel you
into the making tea job I think um
personally I mean I'm just saying
generally okay I'm not talking about
myself personally if you want to talk
about me I have endless projects I have
200 projects I have at least 200
projects closer to 300 maybe and I'm
dying for help I would die to have help
so you know just put your write your
name on a piece of paper and and hand it
to me through the attendance and uh you
know and uh and I
I I love to work with people I love to
you know like Rebecca came to me a year
ago and said I don't have yeah I need a
job guess I said we're going to do this
Retreat you know and uh she said I said
are you up for it and she said yeah I'll
try you know and she's never done this
kind of thing that I know of ever and uh
she said let me take a shot and you know
now she's in my room whispering to me
all day you know we're we're trying to
figure out what to do with the garbage
and stuff
and uh so I would say that I'm I'm very
happy to give jobs and I'm very happy to
have people
close so just just let me know you know
just let me know what your you know come
what your come is what are you good at
what would you like to try like DCI
needs
a we have like 100 uh invitations to
different countries and I don't have the
people to organize those tours I would
love
to that's a real real fun to organize a
tour uh no it is fun it's it's tiring
but it's it's very fulfilling and
rewarding uh because you touch thousands
of people and anybody can do it I think
so I need I need that and a lot of other
things maybe I'll give you a list
towards the end okay I I really need
help uh I what we can do is not limited
by the opportunities it's just limited
by the people by the number of people
okay all
right okay we'll stop there
[Music]
sh
you also have to be persistent okay I'm
the Vietnamese lady from Southern
California I talked to you for 15
minutes at that street and Prescot and
don't forget I want a project you know
so they have to keep sending that email
like six times and
then sometimes I
forget okay